<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>
   <xml> <title>Country Loaf (Pain de Campagne)</title>
    <br/>
    <authorInfo>
        <author>Deb Lindsey</author>
        <transitionWord>for</transitionWord>
        <company><newsOrganization>The Washington Post</newsOrganization></company>
    </authorInfo>
    <br/>
    <date>SEP 10, 2014</date>
    <br/><generalInformation>
    <sentence num="1">Washington author Sam Fromartz has been making sourdough variations of this
        yeast bread for years. Here, he adds fermented cider for flavor. A mild beer may be
        substituted; an IPA would be too bitter. The loaf is sized to last a few days.</sentence>
    <br/>
    <sentence num="2">The optional tablespoon of water is to compensate for the variable absorption
        of the rye and whole-wheat flours. </sentence>
    <br/>
    <sentence num="3">You'll need a colander, a pastry cloth or clean dish towel and a covered
        cast-iron or enameled cast-iron pot.</sentence>
    <br/>
    <sentence num="4">Make Ahead: The dough needs four 20-minute rests, plus an 8-to-24-hour stay in
        the refrigerator and a final 1 1/2-hour rise.</sentence>
    <br/>
    <storageNotes>Storage Notes: Store the cooled loaf in a paper bag for a day, and store in a
        plastic bag for a few days after that. Do not refrigerate.</storageNotes></generalInformation>
    <br/>
    <nutritionInformation num="1">
        <servings> SERVINGS: Tested size: 10-12 servings; makes one 11-ounce loaf 10 to 12 slices
        </servings>
    </nutritionInformation>
    <br/>
    <nutritionInformation num="2">
        <ingredients>
            <title>INGREDIENTS</title>
            <br/>
            <ingredient num="1">1 1/4 cups (160 grams) white bread flour, plus more for
                dusting</ingredient>
            <br/>
            <ingredient num="2">1/4 cup (38 grams) stone-ground whole-wheat flour</ingredient>
            <br/>
            <ingredient num="3">1/4 cup (32 grams) stone-ground whole rye flour</ingredient>
            <br/>
            <ingredient num="4">1/2 teaspoon instant yeast or bread machine yeast</ingredient>
            <br/>
            <ingredient num="5">1 teaspoon table salt</ingredient>
            <br/>
            <ingredient num="6">1/4 cup (55 grams) dry fermented cider (may substitute Pilsener
                beer; see headnote)</ingredient>
            <br/>
            <ingredient num="7">1/2 cup (120 grams) lukewarm water (80 degrees), plus an optional 1
                tablespoon</ingredient>
            <br/>
        </ingredients>
    </nutritionInformation>
    <recipeSteps>
        <directions>
            <recipe>DIRECTIONS <recipeStep num="1">Whisk together the flours, yeast and salt in a
                    mixing bowl. Combine the cider and water in a liquid measuring cup.</recipeStep>
                <br/>
                <recipeStep num="2">Add the liquid to the flour mixture; use a spatula or bench
                    scraper or your hand moistened with water to blend them for about a minute. The
                    dough should be shaggy yet cohesive. Cover the bowl with a towel; let the dough
                    rest for 20 minutes.</recipeStep>
                <br/>
                <recipeStep num="3">Moisten your kneading hand. If the dough seems stiff, add the
                    optional tablespoon of water. Stretch one edge of the dough (still in the bowl),
                    then press it into the center of the bowl. Repeat this about a dozen times,
                    moving clockwise to catch all sides of the dough. (This should take 1 or 2
                    minutes.)</recipeStep>
                <br/>
                <recipeStep num="4">Turn the dough over so the seams are on the bottom. Cover and
                    let rest for 20 minutes. Repeat the clockwise stretching and folding two more
                    times, with 20-minute rests after each. Cover and refrigerate at least 8 hours
                    and up to 24 hours. The dough should have doubled. If it hasn't, leave it on the
                    counter until it does.</recipeStep>
                <br/>
                <recipeStep num="5">Lightly flour a work surface. Use a pastry cloth or clean dish
                    towel to line a round colander. Dust the cloth with flour.</recipeStep>
                <br/>
                <recipeStep num="6">Transfer the dough to the floured work surface. Fold the edges
                    toward the center to create a round shape, turning it over so the seams are on
                    the bottom. Let it rest for 5 minutes, then transfer to the colander, seam side
                    up. Cover with a towel and let the dough rise for 1 1/2 hours.</recipeStep>
                <br/>
                <recipeStep num="7">Thirty minutes before baking, place a cast-iron Dutch oven (lid
                    on) or enameled cast-iron pot with a lid (on) in the oven; preheat to 475
                    degrees.</recipeStep><br/>
                <recipeStep num="8">Carefully remove the hot pot from the oven.</recipeStep>
                <br/>
                <recipeStep num="9">Turn the dough out onto the counter so the seams are on the
                    bottom. Use kitchen scissors to make 8 snips on the top of the dough in an
                    evenly spaced spoke pattern, each about 1/4-inch deep. Lift the dough and
                    carefully drop it into the hot pot. Immediately cover with the hot lid. Bake for
                    30 minutes, then reduce the heat to 450 degrees. Uncover and bake for 8 to 10
                    minutes or until the crust is dark brown. Try to minimize the amount of time the
                    oven door is open.</recipeStep>
                <br/>
                <cookingInformation>The bread is done when its internal temperature registers 205
                    degrees on an instant-read thermometer and the loaf sounds hollow when knocked
                    on the underside.
                    <br/>
                </cookingInformation> Transfer the loaf to a wire rack to cool for at least 1 hour
                before cutting.</recipe>
        </directions>
    </recipeSteps></xml>
</root>
